Once there was a star.
曾经有一颗恒星。
Like everything else, she was born;
像其他的事物一样，她诞生了；
grew to be around 30 times the mass of our sun
她的体积等于我们太阳的30倍，
and lived for a very long time.
存在了一段非常长的时间。
Exactly how long,
到底有多长？
people cannot really tell.
没有人知道。
Just like everything in life,
就像自然界中的一切一样，
she reached the end of her regular star days
她走到了恒星生涯的尽头，
when her heart, the core of her life,
她的内心，生命之核，
exhausted its fuel.
燃尽了所有燃料。
But that was no end.
但这还不是终结。
She transformed into a supernova, and in the process
她转变成了一颗超新星，在这个过程中，
releasing a tremendous amount of energy,
她释放出大量的能量，
outshining the rest of the galaxy
比宇宙其他的一切更闪亮，
and emitting, in one second,
并且，在短短一秒中，释放了相当于
the same amount of energy our sun will release in 10 days.
太阳10天才能释放的能量。
And she evolved into another role in our galaxy.
接着，她进化为我们宇宙中的其他角色。
Supernova explosions are very extreme.
超新星爆炸十分剧烈。
But the ones that emit gamma rays are even more extreme.
但是释放出伽马射线的那一种爆炸更为剧烈。
In the process of becoming a supernova,
在变成超新星的过程中，
the interior of the star collapses under its own weight
恒星的内部由于自身重量过大而坍塌，
and it starts rotating ever faster,
它开始以更快的速度旋转，
like an ice skater when pulling their arms in close to their body.
就像一位将手臂收拢的滑冰者。
In that way, it starts rotating very fast and it increases, powerfully,
以那种方式，它开始飞快旋转，十分快速地增强
its magnetic field.
它的磁场。
The matter around the star is dragged around,
恒星周围的物质被吸引过来，
and some energy from that rotation is transferred to that matter
一些旋转产生的能量也转化成那种物质，
and the magnetic field is increased even further.
磁场随之变得更强了。
In that way, our star had extra energy to outshine the rest of the galaxy
渐渐地，我们的恒星有了额外的能量，在亮度与伽马射线释放量的上
in brightness and gamma ray emission.
比银河系其他部分更耀眼。
My star, the one in my story,
我的故事中的恒星，
became what is known as a magnetar.
就成为了所谓的磁星。
And just for your information,
给大家一个概念，
the magnetic field of a magnetar is 1,000 trillion times the magnetic field of Earth.
磁星的磁场是地球磁场的1,000万亿倍。
The most energetic events ever measured by astronomers
天文学家迄今测量到最为剧烈的活动
carry the name gamma-ray bursts
被命名为伽马射线爆发，
because we observe them as bursts most or explosions,
因为当我们观察它们的时候，我们测量出它们的释放与爆炸程度
most strongly measured as gamma-ray light.
与伽马射线一样强。
Our star, like the one in our story that became a magnetar,
一颗恒星，就像我们的故事中变成磁星的那一颗一样，
is detected as a gamma-ray burst
当爆炸最为剧烈的部分发生时，
during the most energetic portion of the explosion.
就会被检测为伽马射线爆发。
Yet, even though gamma-ray bursts are the strongest events ever measured by astronomers,
然而，即便伽马射线爆发是天文学家迄今为止所测量过最激烈的事件，
we cannot see them with our naked eye.
我们仍旧不能以肉眼看到它们。
We depend, we rely on other methods
我们只能凭借其他的方式
in order to study this gamma-ray light.
来研究这种伽马射线光。
We cannot see them with our naked eye.
我们的肉眼看不到它们。
We can only see an itty bitty, tiny portion
我们只能看到电磁光谱中
of the electromagnetic spectrum that we call visible light.
极其，极其微小的部分，我们称之为可见光。
And beyond that, we rely on other methods.
除此之外，我们也依赖其他方式。
Yet as astronomers, we study a wider range of light
然而作为一名天文学家，我们研究更广的光域，
and we depend on other methods to do that.
也要依赖于其他的方式来实现。
On the screen, it may look like this.
在屏幕上，它也许看起来像这样。
You're seeing a plot.
你们正在看一张曲线图。
That is a light curve.
这是光曲线。
It's a plot of intensity of light over time.
这是关于光强度随着时间变化的图。
It is a gamma-ray light curve.
这是伽马光曲线。
Sighted astronomers depend on this kind of plot
视觉正常的天文学家依赖这种图
in order to interpret how this light intensity changes over time.
来更好地理解光强随时间的变化。
On the left, you will be seeing the light intensity without a burst,
在左侧，你们会看到没有爆发时的光强，
and on the right, you will be seeing the light intensity with the burst.
在右侧，则是有爆发时的光强。
Early during my career, I could also see this kind of plot.
在我事业的早期，我也能看到这样的图。
But then, I lost my sight.
但后来，我失明了。
I completely lost my sight because of extended illness,
由于长期疾病，我完全丧失了视觉，
and with it, I lost the opportunity to see this plot
因此，我失去了看这张图，
and the opportunity to do my physics.
以及从事物理学研究的机会。
It was a very strong transition for me in many ways.
在许多方面，于我而言，都是一段艰难的转变期。
And professionally, it left me without a way to do my science.
从职业的角度上讲，疾病断送了我的科研之路。
I longed to access and scrutinize this energetic light
我渴望接触并揣摩这种能量充沛的光，
and figure out the astrophysical cause.
并探索出天体物理层面的成因。
I wanted to experience the spacious wonder, the excitement,
我想去探索这种巨大的奇迹并体会它带给人的兴奋，
the joy produced by the detection of such a titanic celestial event.
一种探索如此重要的天文事件产生的欢愉。
I thought long and hard about it,
我一直苦思冥想，
when I suddenly realized that all a light curve is,
突然间意识到一切光曲线都是
is a table of numbers converted into a visual plot.
一张转化成可视图的数字表。
So along with my collaborators,
因此我与合作者通力合作，
we worked really hard and we translated the numbers into sound.
绞尽脑汁将数字转化为了声音。
I achieved access to the data,
我实现了对数据的接触与访问，
and today I'm able to do physics at the level of the best astronomer, using sound.
今天，得益于声音，我能以顶尖天文学家的水准从事物理学研究。
And what people have been able to do,
人们已经能够去做的事，
mainly visually,
大多是可视的，
for hundreds of years,
延续了数百年，
now I do it using sound.
如今我以声音实现了。
(Applause)
（掌声）
Listening to this gamma-ray burst
我用听觉感受你们用肉眼（在屏幕上）看到的
that you're seeing on the -- (Applause continues)
肉眼（在屏幕上）看到的
Thank you.
——谢谢—— （掌声持续）
Listening to this burst that you're seeing on the screen
——伽马射线的爆发，
brought something to the ear beyond the obvious burst.
可以给耳朵带来一些超越了单纯爆炸声的东西。
Now I'm going to play the burst for you.
现在，我将为你们播放这一段爆炸声。
It's not music, it's sound.
没有旋律，只是一种声音。
(Digital beeping sounds)
（电子哔哔声）
This is scientific data converted into sound,
这是转换成音波的科学数据，
and it's mapped in pitch.
运用音高的变化来呈现。
The process is called sonification.
这个处理过程称为超声波处理。
So listening to this brought something to the ear
因此聆听这种声音会为耳朵带来
besides the obvious burst.
比简单的爆炸声更多的信息。
When I examine the very strong low-frequency regions,
当我研究这种非常强劲的低频区，
or bass line -- I'm zooming into the bass line now.
或是低音区——我现在切换到低音区部分。
We noted resonances characteristic of electrically charged gasses
我们注意到带电气体的声音回响的特征，
like the solar wind.
就像太阳风。
And I want you to hear what I heard.
现在，我想让你们聆听我所听到的。
You will hear it as a very fast decrease in volume.
你们接下来要到一段急速减弱的声音。
And because you're sighted, I'm giving you a red line
因为你们视觉正常，我会标注一条红线
indicating what intensity of light is being converted into sound.
来指示转换成声音的射线的强度。
(Digital hum and whistling sound)
（电子嗡嗡声和哨声）
The (Whistles) is frogs at home, don't pay attention to that.
那个口哨声是家里的青蛙，请不要在意。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
(Digital hum and whistling sound)
（电子嗡嗡声和哨声）
I think you heard it, right?
你们都听到了吧？
So what we found
我们发现
is that the bursts last long enough in order to support wave resonances,
爆炸要持续足够长才能产生声波回响，
which are things caused by exchanges of energy between particles
回响是由颗粒之间的能量交换产生的，
that may have been excited, that depend on the volume.
不同的音量也许使这些颗粒受到了不同程度的激发。
You may remember that I said that the matter around the star is dragged around?
你们也许记得我讲过恒星周围的物质会被星体拖走。
It transmits power with frequency and field distribution
它传递的能量具有频率和场分布特性，
determined by the dimensions.
这是由维度决定的。
You may remember that we were talking about a super-massive star
你们也许记得我们讲过一颗超重恒星
that became a very strong magnetic field magnetar.
成为了一颗拥有超强磁场的磁星。
If this is the case, then outflows from the exploding star
如果是这样，正在爆炸的恒星发生的喷流
may be associated with this gamma-ray burst.
有可能与这个伽马射线爆发有关。
What does that mean?
这意味着什么？
That star formation may be a very important part of these supernova explosions.
那颗恒星的形成可能是超新星爆炸的重要组成部分。
Listening to this very gamma-ray burst brought us to the notion
聆听伽马射线爆发让我们注意到
that the use of sound as an adjunctive visual display
用声音来辅助视觉显示
may also support sighted astronomers
也许可以同样帮助到正在寻找
in the search for more information in the data.
更多数据资讯的非视障天文学家。
Simultaneously, I worked on analyzing measurements from other telescopes,
同时，我也从事基于其他望远镜的测量分析，
and my experiments demonstrated
我的实验证明了：
that when you use sound as an adjunctive visual display,
当你把声音当作一种辅助性视觉显示工具，
astronomers can find more information in this now more accessible data set.
天文学家就可以在目前可访问的数据集中了解更多信息。
This ability to transform data into sound
这个将数据转化为声音的能力
gives astronomy a tremendous power of transformation.
带给了天文学一种前所未有的强大转换力。
And the fact that a field that is so visual may be improved
场只对视觉正常的人可见的状况得到了改善，
in order to include anyone with interest in understanding what lies in the heavens
让所有对天空感到好奇的人们可以一探究竟，无论视力状况如何。
is a spirit-lifter.
这很让人振奋。
When I lost my sight,
当我失明时，
I noticed that I didn't have access
我注意到我无法和
to the same amount and quality of information a sighted astronomer had.
其它视觉正常的天文家一样获取丰富且高质的信息。
It was not until we innovated with the sonification process
直到我们在超声波处理上有所创新时，
that I regained the hope to be a productive member of the field
我才重新开始希望能为这个领域作出贡献，
that I had worked so hard to be part of.
并为之奋斗。
Yet, information access is not the only area in astronomy where this is important.
然而，获取信息并非是天文学唯一重要的部分。
The situation is systemic
目前它们是互相关联的，
and scientific fields are not keeping up.
但科学界对此尚未跟进。
The body is something changeable --
我们的身体是脆弱的——
anyone may develop a disability at any point.
任何人在任何时候都有致残的可能。
Let's think about, for example,
试想，例如，
scientists that are already at the top of their careers.
那些在各自领域卓有成就的科学家。
What happens to them if they develop a disability?
当他们残疾时会怎么样？
Will they feel excommunicated as I did?
他们会和我一样感到孤独无依吗？
Information access empowers us to flourish.
我们通过获取信息得以发展，
It gives us equal opportunities to display our talents
它给予了我们完全平等的机会来展现自己的才能，
and choose what we want to do with our lives,
让我们可以自主选择自己感兴趣的事情，
based on interest and not based on potential barriers.
而不必受到各种限制。
When we give people the opportunity to succeed without limits,
当人们通往成功的路变得畅通无阻时，
that will lead to personal fulfillment and prospering life.
这将会给他们一种自我满足感，进而带来富足的生活。
And I think that the use of sound in astronomy
我认为声音在天文学中的应用
is helping us to achieve that and to contribute to science.
正帮助我们达成这个目标，并促进科学的发展。
While other countries told me that the study of perception techniques
然而其他国家告知我以研究天文数据为目的的
in order to study astronomy data is not relevant to astronomy
感知技术的研究与天文学无关，
because there are no blind astronomers in the field,
因为目前这个领域还没有视障的天文学家，
South Africa said, "We want people with disabilities
南非的表态是，“我们希望残疾人士
to contribute to the field."
可以为这个领域贡献自己的力量。”
Right now, I'm working at the South African Astronomical Observatory,
于是目前，我正在南非天文观测站的
at the Office of Astronomy for Development.
天文学发展性研究办公室工作。
There, we are working on sonification techniques and analysis methods
在那里，我们利用超声波处理技术以及分析手段
to impact the students of the Athlone School for the Blind.
帮助阿斯隆盲人学校的学生。
These students will be learning radio astronomy,
这些学生将会学习射电天文学，
and they will be learning the sonification methods
以及利用超声波处理方法
in order to study astronomical events like huge ejections of energy
来研究天文事件，比如研究从太阳喷射出的巨大能量，
from the sun, known as coronal mass ejections.
就是你们熟知的日冕物质抛射。
What we learn with these students --
我们从这些学生身上学到了——
these students have multiple disabilities and coping strategies that will be accommodated --
这些学生罹患多重残疾，但我们有应对的方法——
what we learn with these students will directly impact
我们从这些学生上学到的经验会影响
the way things are being done at the professional level.
我们在专业领域处理事情的做法。
I humbly call this development.
我把它称之为“发展”。
And this is happening right now.
现在，“发展”正在发生。
I think that science is for everyone.
我认为科学是每个人的。
It belongs to the people,
它属于全人类，
and it has to be available to everyone,
它应当对所有人都敞开大门，
because we are all natural explorers.
因为我们都是天生的探索者。
I think that if we limit people with disabilities
我认为如果人们因为残疾而被限制，
from participating in science,
不能参与到科学活动中来，
we'll sever our links with history and with society.
历史与社会的桥梁将因此轰塌。
I dream of a level scientific playing field,
我向往一个公平的科研竞争环境，
where people encourage respect and respect each other,
人们相互鼓励与尊重，
where people exchange strategies and discover together.
相互交换自己的策略和研究发现。
If people with disabilities are allowed into the scientific field,
如果残疾人得以获得科学领域的入场券，
an explosion, a huge titanic burst of knowledge will take place,
知识之泉将以洪荒之力爆发、喷涌，
I am sure.
我很确信这一点。
(Digital beeping sounds)
（电子哔哔声）
That is the titanic burst.
这是一次激烈的喷涌。
Thank you.
谢谢。
(Applause)
（掌声）